<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.1">
    <info>
        <title>Page numbers in xslTNG printed media</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Frank</firstname><surname>Steimke</surname></personname>
            <email>fsteimke.hb@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <date>2022-05-05</date>
    </info>
    <dedication>
        <title>Dedication</title>
        <para>An dedication could be placed here</para>
    </dedication>
    <preface>
        <title>Preface</title>
        <para>This book examines the handling of page numbers in CSS printed media. It is both
            documentation and its own illustrative material. It is created in DocBook format and
            converted to HTML with xslTNG 2.2. It is then rendered to PDF using various rendering
            engines. The aim is to illustrate the problems that can occur with page numbers in the
            created PDF and how these can be solved.</para>
        <para>Some of the problematic effects are only recognizable when sections in the generated
            PDF contain a page break. For this reason, some sections of this book are more extensive
            and detailed than is absolutely necessary. It is expressly intended to fill pages,
            because we need page breaks for illustration. Also, it's the first time for me to have a
                <tag>dedication</tag> and a <tag>colophon</tag> in a book. It's only because I
            wanted to see them rendered in PDF.</para>
        <para>This book is translated with DeepL.com from german.</para>
    </preface>
    <chapter>
        <title>Motivation</title>
        <para>DocBook <citation>DB 5.2 </citation>is a general purpose XML schema for structured
            documents. It's an OASIS Standard. Yo have to transform them into output formats like
            HTML, PDF or ODF before the audience can read them. For this, you have to use
            stylesheets.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="italic">DocBook: xslTNG</emphasis> are the next generation of DocBook
            stylesheets following on from the <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/docbook/xslt20-stylesheets"><emphasis role="italic"
                    >DocBook XSLT 2.0 Stylesheets</emphasis></link> and the <link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/docbook/xslt10-stylesheets"><emphasis role="italic"
                    >DocBook XSLT 1.0 Stylesheets</emphasis></link> that preceded them. They
            transform DocBook XML documents into clean, semantically rich HTML5. A CSS stylesheet
            suitable for online presentation is included.</para>
        <para>Producing high quality print output with a paged media capable CSS processor is also
            supported.This is explained in Section 2.1.4 of <citation>xslTNG Ref</citation>, which
            says: <quote>At present, the <emphasis role="italic">DocBook xslTNG
                    Stylesheets</emphasis> are focused on CSS for print output. There’s a
                customization layer that produces “paged-media-ready” HTML that can be processed
                with a CSS formatter such as <link
                    xlink:href="https://xsltng.docbook.org/guide/2.2.0/references#AntennaHouse"
                    >Antenna House</link> or <link
                    xlink:href="https://xsltng.docbook.org/guide/2.2.0/references#Prince"
                    >Prince</link></quote>.</para>
        <para>Both are commercial products. This creates a high barrier to entry for all those who
            want to create not only HTML but also PDF with the stylesheets. For the success of
            xslTNG stylesheets, it is therefore necessary to support products that are associated
            with no or only low costs. </para>
        <para>You can find an excellent tutorial that shows how to generate PDF documents from
            XML/HTML using the "CSS Paged Media" approach at <link
                xlink:href="https://print-css.rocks/">print-css.rocks</link>. It's not only a
            tutorial, they do also test various CSS Paged Media converters . WeasyPrint (<link
                xlink:href="https://weasyprint.org/">weasyprint.org/</link>) is a free and open
            source software for rendering HTML into PDF, so I  gave it a try. The result was
            promising, but there was a problem: references to pages (for example in the table of
            contents, but also in cross-references) do not show the correct page number, but always
            a 0 (zero). I found Issue 433 which complains about the same problem. It already
            identified <code>counter-reset: page</code> as problem (<quote>Apparently weasyprint
                doesn't like that</quote>), but was closed with an only half-hearted solution:
                <code>ounter-reset: none</code> leads to correct page numbers, but the first page
            for content in the book (after the <emphasis>Titlepage</emphasis>, the
                <emphasis>Table(s) of Content</emphasis> and other stuff like that) does not start
            with page number <quote>1</quote>.</para>
        <para>This led to an error message at weasyprint (<link
                xlink:href="https://github.com/Kozea/WeasyPrint/issues/2114">Issue 2114</link>). The
            developer provides a comprehensible explanation and a solution that delivers the desired
            result with weasyprint. However, the solution does not work properly with Antenna House.
            This doesn't look like an bug to me. On the contrary, Weasyprint's approach seems to me
            to be problematic in conjunction with CSS <quote>named pages</quote>, so that I can
            understand Antenna House's result better than Weasyprint's.</para>
        <para>However, I am anything but an expert in CSS paged media. I am not in a position to
            decide which implementation is right and which is wrong. Therefore, I have decided to
            document both approaches with the corresponding results as well as possible, so that an
            optimal solution for the xslTNG stylesheets can be developed. In addition to Antenna
            House and Weasyprint, the product <link
                xlink:href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/chemistry-html-to-pdf-converter.html">PDF
                Chemistry</link> from Syncro Soft will also be examined. It is part of the Oxygen
            product family and can be used free of charge by users of the Oxygen IDE to convert
            HTML+CSS paged media into PDF. PDF Chemistry is a CSS Paged Media processor based on the
            open-source Apache FOP XSL-FO engine. In other words, in transforms HTML+CSS into <link
                xlink:href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xsl11/">XSL Formatting Objects (XSL-FO)</link>
            which can be rendered into PDF with the open source <link
                xlink:href="https://xmlgraphics.apache.org/fop/">FOP Software from Apache</link>,
            which also ships with Oxygen.</para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Test approach and results</title>
        <section>
            <title>This Report is the Test-Document</title>
            <para>This report here serves as the base HTML Document for the test of CSS Sytlesheets
                and rendering engines. It is written in DocBook 5.1. The xslTNG Stylesheets Version
                2.2 with <filename>print.xsl</filename> are used to produce the HTML file
                    <filename>report.html</filename>.</para>
            <para>Parameter <code>page-style</code> is set to <code>book</code>.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Rendering Engines</title>
            <para>It was tested with these software products: </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">WeasyPrint version 54.1</emphasis> on Ubuntu Linux.
                        It is used as</para>
                    <programlisting>weasyprint -s css-file report.html report.pdf</programlisting>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">PDF Chemistry, part of XML Editor 26.0</emphasis> on
                        Ubuntu Linux. To use it within Oxygen, I had to define <quote>transformation
                            scenarios</quote> of type <quote>XML to PDF transformation with
                            CSS</quote> which refers the <code>css-file</code>. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">Antenna House Formatter 7.4R1</emphasis> on Windows
                        10. It is used as</para>
                    <programlisting>ahfcmd.exe -css css-file -d report.html -o report.pdf</programlisting>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>xslTNG CSS</title>
            <para>xslTNG brings it's own CSS stylesheets for HTML as well as PDF. When the parameter
                    <code>use-docbook-css</code> is set to <code>true</code> (the default), the HTML
                file will refer to CSS like this:</para>
            <programlisting>&lt;link href="./css/docbook.css" rel="stylesheet" media="screen" />
&lt;link href="./css/docbook-paged.css" rel="stylesheet" media="print" /></programlisting>
            <section>
                <title>Weasyprint</title>
                <para>Weasyprint produces a PDF file which looks fine at the first glance, but all
                    page numbers in the ToC are 0 (Zero):</para>
                <informalfigure>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="tng-css-wp-toc.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>
            </section>
            <section>
                <title>PDF Chemistry crashes with NPE</title>
                <para>Oxygen's PDF Chemistry complains about <code>invalid 'target-counter' function
                        signature. Must be target-counter( &lt;url-fragment> , &lt;custom-ident> [ ,
                        &lt;counter-style></code> with a Warning. It crashes with this message:
                        <code>java.lang.NullPointerException: Cannot invoke
                        "ro.sync.ecss.css.functions.kb.l(String)" because the return value of
                        "ro.sync.ecss.css.functions.ab.c()" is null</code>.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
    </chapter>
    <bibliography>
        <title>Bibliography</title>
        <bibliomixed><abbrev>db 5.2</abbrev><title>DocBook 5.2: The Definitive Guide</title> by <author>
                <personname><firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname></personname>
            </author>. Online available at <link xlink:href="https://tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.2/"
                >tdg.docbook.org/tdg/5.2/</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed><abbrev>xslTNG</abbrev><title> DocBook xslTNG</title> by <author>
                <personname><firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname></personname>
            </author>. Online available at <link xlink:href="https://xsltng.docbook.org/"
                >xsltng.docbook.org/</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed><abbrev>xslTNG Ref</abbrev><title>DocBook xslTNG Reference</title> by <author>
                <personname><firstname>Norman</firstname><surname>Walsh</surname></personname>
            </author>. Online available at <link xlink:href="https://xsltng.docbook.org/guide/"
                >xsltng.docbook.org/guide/</link></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
    <colophon>
        <title>Why you should read this Book (Colophon)</title>
        <para>It is written in DocBook 5.1. Translated to HTML with xslTNG 2.2.</para>
        <para>Rendered in PDF with different engines: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Antenna House</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>WeasyPrint</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PDF Chemistry (part of the Oxygen XML Suite)</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>
    </colophon>
</book>
